Guide to the David B. McCall Papers, 1939-1999 and undated, bulk 1980-1994
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Speeches Series, 1958-1990 and undated, (3 boxes)
  - Speeches by McCall Subseries, 1958-1990 and undated (Box 23)
    - Advertising-Research
      - American Research Foundation, comments on Dr. Leavitt's speech, 1961 (Box 24)
      - The One-Percent Solution, 1984 (Box 24)
      - Wall Street Journal conference, 1981 (Box 24)
      - What an Advertising Agency's Management Wants from Marketing Research, 1973 (Box 24)
    - Commencement Addresses
      - Basic advertising course, AAAA, 1970 (Box 24)
      - Hotchkiss School, 1969 (Box 24)
      - Rumson County Day School, ca. 1973 (Box 24)
    - Social-Political
      - AAAA (American Association of Advertising Agencies) annual meeting, 1972 (Box 24)
      - Advertising and Social Responsibility, 1972 (Box 24)
      - Advertising in a Period of Transition and Uncertainty, 1974 (Box 24)
      - Comments on a talk by Bill Claggett on advertising in the 1970s, undated (Box 24)
      - FTC speech-responses and background, 1982 (See also Oversize Materials, Oversize Box OV3.), (2 folders) (Box 24)
      - McGovern speech, 1972 (Box 24)
      - Political Advertising: The Product of Saints or Sinners? 1977 (Box 24)
      - Sex, Religion, Politics, Positioning and Other 1973 Breakthroughs, 1973 (Box 24)
      - Up in Smoke: The Great Cigarette Debate, 1987, 1989
        - Copies of speech, (2 folders) (Box 24)
        - Supporting Materials (Box 24)
      - What Agencies Are--And Aren't--Doing, 1968 (Box 24)
      - What Does Advertising Owe Society? 1966 (Box 24)
      - Young Republicans, 1967 (Box 24)
    - Testimonial
      - Jim Manning, in verse, 1978 (Box 24)
      - On the retirement of Jim McCaffrey, ca. 1973 (Box 24)
      - The New Yorker and Me: A 40-Year-Old Love Affair, 1980 (Box 24)
      - Wallace Clayton, in verse, undated (Box 24)
        Clayton was an executive at McCaffrey & McCall, and formerly of the J. Walter Thompson Company.
      - Wallace Quimby, undated (Box 24)
    - Speech file (See also Oversize Materials, Oversize Box OV3.)
      Notes, communication, clippings collected for use in speech-writing.
      - Clippings, 1953-1990 (See also Oversize Materials, Oversize Box OV3.) (Box 24)
      - Correspondence, 1967-1984 (See also Oversize Materials, Oversize Box OV3.), (2 folders) (Box 24)
      - Notes and research for a speech on advertising awards, ca. 1974 (Box 25)
  - Speeches by Others Subseries, 1958-1990
    - Bailey, Patricia: testimony before the Senate Subcommittee on the Consumer, 1982 (Box 25)
    - Bell, Howard: State of the Federation address, American Advertising Federation, 1982 (Box 25)
    - Blair, Bill: Incidentally, 1958 (Box 25)
    - Booth, William: Opening remarks, Advertising and Broadcasting Industries Hearing (New York, N.Y.), 1968 (Box 25)
    - Elliott, John: Acceptance speech, Maj. Gen. John W. Russell Leadership Award, 1989 (Box 25)
      John Elliott was Chairman Emeritus at Ogilvy & Mather.
    - Hernandez Colon, Rafael: speech made during a visit to Harvard University, 1990 (Box 25)
      Rafael Hernandez Colon was Governor of Puerto Rico.
    - Jaffe, Daniel: Report from Washington, 1982 (Box 25)
    - Ross, Warren: We Have Met the Censor and He Is Us, 1973 (Box 25)
- Writings Series, 1939-1997 and undated, (1 box)
  Includes letters to the editors of various publications, journal articles, poetry and other writings by McCall, along with a small collection of writings by others. The series is organized into two subseries--Writings by McCall and Writings by Others. Writings by McCall are arranged into five categories--advertising-related, autobiographical writings, letters to the editor, poetry and literature, and social-political--and alphabetically therein. Writings by Others are arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Writings by McCall Subseries, 1961-1997 and undated (Box 25)
    - Advertising-related
      - Advertising copy and radio spot texts, drafts, undated (Box 25)
      - For Talent, Three Virtually Untapped Areas, The Copywriter, 1963 Nov. 29 (Box 25)
      - Good Product, or A Copywriter's Best Friend, Madison Avenue, 1963 Aug. (Box 25)
      - How to Become a copywriter from Some Other Job in Y&R, undated (Box 25)
      - Monster Trout in the Media Pool, 1979 (Box 25)
        Submitted to Magazine Age.
      - Research and the Copy Writer, 1961 (Box 25)
      - Telecommunications spots, drafts, 1991 (Box 25)
      - Thoughts of a CEO, undated (Box 25)
      - What's the Big Deal? 1987 (Box 25)
    - Autobiographical writings, undated (Box 25)
    - Letters to the editor
      - Advertising Age, 1973-1974, (2 folders) (Box 25)
      - International Herald Tribune, Land Mine Ban is Just a First Step, (Op Ed piece), 1997 Nov. 13 (Box 25)
      - New York Magazine, 1970 Oct. 15 (Box 25)
      - New York Times, 1970, 1995, (2 folders) (Box 25)
    - Poetry and Literature
      - Book project, My Daddy's in the Advertising Business, ca. 1987 (Box 25)
      - Movie ideas
        - Bore, 1987 (Box 25)
        - I'd Rather Be Right, undated (Box 25)
        - Rent a Cop, undated (Box 25)
      - Poetry project, 1978, (2 folders) (Box 25)
    - Social-political
      - Book project, Voices from the Future, undated (Box 25)
        Planned as profiles of refugee children.
      - Easter Manifesto, 1991 (Box 25)
      - If It Ain't Broke, Don't Fix It, undated (Box 25)
      - Memorandum on the Role of the Vice-President, 1972 (Box 25)
      - My Turn: Rich Family Values, ca. 1989 (Box 25)
        On the first Bush administration and affluent neoconservatives.
      - Profit: Spur for Solving Social Ills, 1973 (Box 25)
      - United States and the New World Disorder, 1992 (Box 25)
      - Wingate's Raiders: A Proposal, ca. 1969 (Box 25)
  - Writings by Others Subseries, 1939-1990 and undated
    - Brown, Mark Malloch, untitled article on Mario Vargas Llosa, 1990 (Box 25)
      Draft submitted to McCall for review. Vargas Llosa, the Peruvian novelist, was a onetime candidate for the presidency of Peru and a client of the Sawyer Miller Group. For other material in this collection relating to Vargas Llosa, see Box 14.
    - Cullum, Paul, Forward Lateral, 1987 (Box 25)
      Film script submitted to McCall for review.
    - Gramm, Eugene: We Must Love One Another Or Die, 1982 (Box 25)
      Eugene Gramm was Creative Supervisor at the Marsteller, Inc. advertising agency.
    - Multiple authors, collection of scientific reprints relating to carbonated beverages, 1939-1952 and undated (Box 25)
    - Yang, Charles: The Place of Games in Advertising Education, 1971 (Box 25)
      Includes memo from Wilson Siebert of J. Walter Thompson to David McCall.
- Portfolio Series, 1951-1992 and undated, (2 boxes)
  Contains materials relating primarily to McCall's early career, first at Young & Rubicam, then at Ogilvy & Mather and David J. Mahoney, Inc. Materials were originally placed in scrapbooks, but over the course of time had loosened into individual items. Clients represented include Life Magazine, the American Can Company, Lever Brothers and the Zippo Manufacturing Company. The series is organized by alphabetically by advertising agency and client name.
  - David J. Mahoney, Inc., 1955 and undated (Box PF1)
    McCall worked as copy writer for the Mahoney agency from 1953-1955.
    - Clients and Products
      - Noxzema Shaving Creme (Box PF1)
      - Reynolds & Co. (Box PF1)
      - S.A. Schonbrunn & Co. (Medaglia d'Oro coffee) (Box PF1)
      - S.B. Thomas, Inc. (Thomas's English Muffins) (Box PF1)
      - Sparton Radio-Television (Box PF1)
      - Sportsman Shaving Lotion, Inc. (Box PF1)
      - Virginia Dare Wine (Box PF1)
      - White Rock (Box PF1)
  - McCaffrey & McCall, 1981
    - Poster for Creative Advertising Challenge (Box PF1)
  - Ogilvy Benson & Mather
    - Clients and Products
      - C-L, 1951-1963 (Box PF1)
        Includes Calvert Distillers, Chase National Bank, Christian Brothers, Cunard Lines, Goodenham & Wortz (G&W), Hathaway Shirts, Jaguar, KLM Airlines, Lord & Taylor.
      - Lever Brothers, Rinso, 1953 and undated (Box PF1)
      - P-T, 1952-1961 and undated (Box PF1)
        Includes Pepperidge Farm, Philip Morris (Spud Cigarettes), Sears, Schweppes, Tetley Tea, True Confessions.
      - Thom McCann Shoes, 1955-1956 (Box PF1)
      - True Magazine, ca. 1952 (Box PF1)
      - Zippo Manufacturing Co., 1957-1959 (Box PF1)
    - Clippings, 1959 (Box PF1)
  - The Orwell Agency (also known as the Maxwell Arnold Agency), ca. 1970 (Box PF1)
    Mission statement, print advertisement.
  - Young & Rubicam, 1951 (Box PF2)
    - Clients and Products
      - American Can Company (CANCO), (2 folders) (Box PF2)
      - Borden's Dog Food (Box PF2)
      - Corning Glass Works (Box PF2)
      - Dictaphone (Box PF2)
      - General Electric (Box PF2)
      - Life Magazine, (6 folders) (Box PF2)
      - Statler Hotels (Box PF2)
  - Various loose materials (Box PF1)
    - Artwork and layout, undated (Box PF1)
    - Photograph, undated (Box PF1)
    - Calendar, Segeln '92, 1992 (Box PF1)
- Audiovisual Materials Series, 1989-1998 and undated, (6 boxes)
  Includes documentary and promotional short films, commercials and radio spot announcements, primarily for pro bono projects such as Refugees International and the Committee to Support Roe v. Wade. Originals are dated 1989-1998 and undated. Arranged into three catgories--Original Materials, Master Copies, and Use Copies--therein by format and then alphabetically.
  Originals closed to patron use. Some use copies available in the collection. Otherwise, Technical Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed. Please consult with Research Services staff before coming to use this collection.
  - Original Materials (CLOSED)
    - Videocassettes (CLOSED)
      - OR1. Bank Street School, 16 mm reel, undated (Box AV1)
        Use Copy UC1 in Box AV6.
      - OR2. Care, My Opportunity, VHS, 1997-1998 (Box AV2)
        Use Copy UC2 in Box AV6.
      - OR3. Care, PSA spots, VHS, undated (Box AV2)
      - OR4. Demining with Steel Wheels in Mozambique, VHS, 1997 Oct.-Nov. (Box AV2)
      - OR5. Georgia Power, Faces Behind the Image, VHS, 1997 Aug. 13 (Box AV2)
        Use Copy UC4 in Box AV6.
      - OR6. Lincoln Unified School District, Imagine the Lincoln Plan, VHS, undated (Box AV2)
        Use Copy UC3 in Box AV6.
      - OR7. Paul Keye & Partners, VHS, 1996 May, 15 (Box AV2)
      - OR8. Refugees International, Demining the Killing Fields, VHS, undated (Box AV2)
      - OR9. Roe v. Wade spot, evening edit, Umatic, 1989 Apr. 10 (Box AV2)
        Use Copy UC5 in Box AV6.
      - OR10. Roe v. Wade spot, Live-a-matic edit, Umatic, undated (Box AV2)
      - OR11. Xerox do Brasil, Ltda., Community Development Projects, VHS, undated (Box AV2)
      - OR12. Western Placer Unified School District, Project Build, undated (Box AV2)
    - Sound recordings (CLOSED)
      - D.J. Mahoney, Inc. radio spots, 12-inch vinyl (Box AV3)
        - OR13. Demonstration record, 1955 Oct. 24 (Box AV3)
          Use Copy UC6 in Box AV6.
        - OR14. Medaglia D'Oro, 1956 Jan. 6 (Box AV3)
        - OR15. Virginia Dare Wine, 1955 (Box AV3)
      - OR16. Multiplication Rock, original soundtrack recording, 12-inch phonograph, 1973 (Box AV3)
        Use Copy UC7 in Box AV6.
    - Tape recordings (CLOSED)
      - Roe v. Wade, Committee to Support Roe v. Wade radio spots, 1/4-inch reel-to-reel audio tape (Box AV4)
        - Celebrity endorsements
          - OR17. RDRW 9861, 9862, 9863, 9864, 1989 Apr. 7 (Box AV4)
          - OR18A. RDRW 9862, 1989 Apr. 12 (Box AV4)
          - OR18B. RDRW 9862, 1989 Apr. 12 (Box AV4)
          - OR19. RDRW 9868, 1989 Apr. 17 (Box AV4)
        - OR20. Eventime, 1989 Apr. 13 (Box AV4)
  - Master Copies (Not for reference use)
    - MC1 (Box AV5)
      Format: BetacamSP. Source: OR1. Date created: 2005.
      - Bank Street School, undated (Box AV5)
    - MC2
      Format: BetacamSP. Source: OR2-OR4, OR8. Date created: 2005.
      - Care, My Opportunity, 1997-1998 (Box AV5)
      - Care, PSA spots, undated (Box AV5)
      - Demining with Steel Wheels in Mozambique, 1997 Oct.-Nov. (Box AV5)
      - Refugees International, Demining the Killing Fields, undated (Box AV5)
    - MC3
      Format: BetacamSp. Source: OR6-OR7, OR12. Date created: 2005.
      - Lincoln Unified School District, Imagine the Lincoln Plan, undated (Box AV5)
      - Paul Keye & Partners, 1996 May, 15 (Box AV5)
      - Western Placer Unified School District, Project Build, undated (Box AV5)
    - MC4
      Format: BetacamSp. Source: OR5, OR11. Date created: 2005.
      - Georgia Power, Faces Behind the Image, 1997 Aug. 13 (Box AV5)
      - Xerox do Brasil, Ltda., Community Development Projects, undated (Box AV5)
    - MC5
      Format: BetacamSP. Source: OR9-OR10. Date created: 2005.
      - Roe v. Wade spot, evening edit, 1989 Apr. 10 (Box AV5)
      - Roe v. Wade spot, Live-a-matic edit, undated (Box AV5)
    - OR13-20 Data Files (Box AV5)
      Format: DVD-RW. Source: OR13-OR20. Date created: 2006.
    - PC6
      Format: DVD-RW. Source: OR13-OR15, OR17-OR20. Date created: 2006.
      - D.J. Mahoney demo recording, 1955 (Box AV5)
      - Medaglio d'Oro coffee spot, 1956 (Box AV5)
      - Virginia Dare pink wine spot, 1955 (Box AV5)
      - Committee to Support Roe v. Wade radio spots, 1989 (Box AV5)
    - PC7
      Format: DVD-RW. Source: OR16. Date created: 2006.
      - Multiplication Rock, 1973 (Box AV5)
  - Use Copies
    - UC1 (Box AV6)
      Format: DVD. Source: OR1. Date created: 2005.
      - Bank Street School, undated (Box AV6)
    - UC2
      Format: DVD. Source: OR2-OR4, OR8. Date created: 2005.
      - Care, My Opportunity,, 1997-1998 (Box AV6)
      - Care, PSA spots, undated (Box AV6)
      - Demining with Steel Wheels in Mozambique,, 1997 Oct.-Nov. (Box AV6)
      - Refugees International, Demining the Killing Fields,, undated (Box AV6)
    - UC3
      Format: DVD. Source: OR6-OR7, OR12. Date created: 2005.
      - Lincoln Unified School District, Imagine the Lincoln Plan,, undated (Box AV6)
      - Paul Keye & Partners, 1996 May, 15 (Box AV6)
      - Western Placer Unified School District, Project Build, undated (Box AV6)
    - UC4
      Format: DVD. Source: OR5, OR11. Date created: 2005.
      - Georgia Power, Faces Behind the Image,, 1997 Aug. 13 (Box AV6)
      - Xerox do Brasil, Ltda., Community Development Projects, undated (Box AV6)
    - UC5
      Format: DVD. Source: OR9-OR10. Date created: 2005.
      - Roe v. Wade spot, evening edit, 1989 Apr. 10 (Box AV6)
      - Roe v. Wade spot, Live-a-matic edit, undated (Box AV6)
    - UC6
      - D.J. Mahoney demo recording, 1955 (Box AV6)
      - Medaglio d'Oro coffee spot, 1956 (Box AV6)
      - Virginia Dare pink wine spot, 1955 (Box AV6)
      - Committee to Support Roe v. Wade radio spots, 1989 (Box AV6)
    - UC7
      - Multiplication Rock, 1973 (Box AV6)
- Oversize Materials, 1962-1993
  - McCaffrey & McCall Series, 1979, 1987 and undated
    - Artwork and storyboards, campaign for American Association of Retired Persons (AARP), ca. 1987 (See also box 5.) (Box OV1)
    - Bound materials
      - Call for Action, flipbook, undated (Box OV2)
      - North American Philips Corp., 25th anniversary bound scrapbook, 1979 (See also Box 5.) (Box OV2)
  - Hunter Fan Company Series, 1992-1993
    - Advertising, 1992 (See also Box 16.) (Box OV3)
    - Artwork and storyboards, ca. 1993 (See also Box 16.) (Box OV3)
    - Board of Directors
      - Meeting, 1992 Mar. (See also Box 17.) (Box OV3)
        Includes Hunter Fan promotional poster.
  - McCaffrey & McCall Series, 1964-1991 and undated
    - Administrative Files (Box OV3)
      - Public Relations, The Publicist, 1982 May-June (See also Box 2.) (Box OV3)
    - Clients-Commercial (Other client-related files for this Series are located in Boxes 3-6.)
      - Allied Fiber, undated (Box OV3)
      - Mercedes-Benz of North America, 1985, 1988 (See also Box 3.) (Box OV3)
      - Numismatic Funding Corporation, undated (Box OV3)
      - Sears (Corporate), 1981 (Box OV3)
        Includes note from Joel Raphaelson.
      - Sears print advertisements, undated (Box OV3)
      - Video Visions Associates, 1985 (See also Box 4.), (2 folders) (Box OV3)
      - Print of poster by David Mattingly for the Inglett-Watson Travel Poster Exhibition, 1977 (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Clients-House/Agency Advertisements (Box OV3)
      - Jim Manning retirement advertisement, 1978 (See also Box 4.) (Box OV3)
    - Clients-New Business
      - Automotive study, 1984 (Box OV3)
    - Clients-Political
      - Princeton Republicans for Johnson, 1964 (Box OV3)
    - Clients-Pro Bono, Public Service and Nonprofit
      - Committee for the Support of Roe v. Wade, 1991 (See also Box 5.) (Box OV3)
      - New York Urban League, 1964 (See also Box 5.) (Box OV3)
      - Tobacco Advertising, Tobacco and Youth Report, 1989 Spring (See also Box 5.) (Box OV3)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda
      - J.C. Penney and agency advertisements removed from correspondence, 1978, 1984 (See also Box 7.) (Box OV3)
    - Printed Materials (See also Box 5.)
      - Advertising Age, 1983 June 27 (Box OV3)
        Article on sale of McCaffrey & McCall to Saatchi & Saatchi.
      - Artwork, undated (Box OV3)
  - Ogilvy & Mather Series, 1962 (See also Box 1.)
    - Correspondence (Box OV3)
      - Gerard Lambert, with Listerine Advertisement, 1962 (Box OV3)
  - Radio Stations Series, 1988 (See also Box 8.)
    - Proposed Acquisitions (Box OV3)
      - Copies of Dundee Observer and Lake Country Drummer, 1988 (Box OV3)
        Dundee, N.Y. local newspapers.
  - Sawyer Miller Group Series, 1990-1991
    - Clients-Commercial (Box OV3)
      - Regional Bells, advertising strategy, 1991 (See also Boxes 12-13.) (Box OV3)
      - Puerto Rico Telephone Company (PRTC), 1990 (See also Box 11.) (Box OV3)
  - Refugees International Series, 1992-1993
    - Activities, Cambodia/Thailand, copies of Cambodian newspapers, 1992 (See also Box 20.) (Box OV3)
    - Correspondence, Ethnic Wars Multiply, New York Times, 1993 Feb. 7 (See also Box 22.) (Box OV3)
  - Speeches Series, 1978-1989
    - FTC speech, responses and background, 1982 (See also Box 24.) (Box OV3)
    - Speech File, John Hollander, Inigo Jones, Tampa Tribune, 1984 (See also Boxes 24-25.) (Box OV3)
    - The Joy of Advertising, correspondence, 1989 (See also Box 23.) (Box OV3)
    - The Many Faces of Print, supporting materials, 1978 (See also Box 23.) (Box OV3)